Dr. Travis J. Kessler

Easton, NY 12154 (978) 201-7710

travis.j.kessler@gmail.com https://www.traviskessler.com https://github.com/tjkessler

Machine learning and software engineer with more than ten years of experience in academic research and open-source software development. Confident in directing teammates and students as a project manager and instructor. Recipient of multiple first-place engineering and entrepreneurial competition awards. Achievements include successfully developing machine learning models to efficiently discover cleaner, renewable, and economically-viable liquid fuels and fuel additives. Skilled in applied machine learning, data mining and processing, probability and statistics, and software engineering development and management.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Python, C/C++, MATLAB
- TensorFlow/Keras, PyTorch
- Scikit-learn, NumPy, Pandas
- Jupyter Notebook
- Ray/Dask

- Predictive/statistical modeling
- Clustering and classification
- Regression and transformers
- Data visualization
- Web scraping

- AWS, GCS, Azure
- SQL (Postgres, MySQL)
- NoSQL (MongoDB)
- Git/SVN
- Docker

EDUCATION

PhD, Computer Engineering University of Massachusetts Lowell May 2023 B.S., Computer Engineering University of Massachusetts Lowell May 2018

EXPERIENCE

Research Engineer

AIMdyn, Inc.

Oct. 2023 — Present

- Utilizes Koopman Operator Theory-based generative AI and other cutting-edge machine learning methods for the analysis, prediction, and control of complex dynamical systems
- Implements modular and scalable data processing, model training, and hyper-parameter tuning pipelines
- Administrates server cluster workflow/job manager, oversees software/application deployments, and manages network configurations

Graduate Researh Assistant

Jan. 2019 — Sep. 2023

University of Massachusetts Lowell Energy & Combustion Research Laboratory

- Leveraged predictive models (deep learning, graph neural networks, etc.) to advance alternative fuel research
- Investigated methods for neural network feature selection and hyper-parameter tuning, including random forest trees, principal component analysis, artificial bee colonies, and various optimization algorithms
- Evaluated predictor/target variable relationships using a variety of statistical methods
- Managed a team of undergraduate computer science/engineering students to support research efforts
- Published research efforts in The Proceedings of the Combustion Institute, The Journal of Open Source Software, and the American Society of Mechanical Engineers Internal Combustion Engine Fall Conference

Implementation/DevOps Engineer

June 2018 — Jan. 2019

Valora Technologies

- Extracted text/numerical information from legal, financial, and government documents
- Constructed data pipelines to usher client documents from intake to delivery of data (ETL)
- Trained newly hired Implementation/DevOps engineers in data pipelining/mining workflow configuration

University of Massachusetts Lowell Energy & Combustion Research Laboratory

- Optimized predictive models to predict chemical properties based on molecular structure (QSAR/QSPR)
- Implemented optimal neural network architectures for multidimensional input and target data
- Developed open-source machine learning, feature extraction, and hyper-parameter tuning software packages
- Published research efforts in Fuel, The Journal of Open Source Software, and the American Society of Mechanical Engineers Internal Combustion Engine Fall Conference

SELECTED AWARDS & HONORS

Dean's Gold Medal for Outstanding Academic Achievement	$May \ 2023$
Computer Engineering Department Award for Outstanding Ph.D.	May 2023
Best Presentation, ASME ICEF 2019 Conference	Oct. 2019
1^{st} place, Symbotic Warehouse Robot Prototyping Competition	May 2018
Innovative Technology Solution, UMass Lowell DifferenceMaker 50K Idea Challenge	$April\ 2017$
1 st place, Francis College of Engineering Prototyping Competition	Dec. 2016

PUBLISHED WORKS

- PB12. Fnu Gorky, Apolo Nambo, **Travis J. Kessler**, J. Hunter Mack, Maria L. Carreon. " CO_2 and HPDE Upcycling: A Plasma Catalysis Alternative". Industrial & Engineering Chemistry Research (2023). https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.iecr.3c02403
- PB11. Amina SubLaban, **Travis Kessler**, Noah Van Dam, J. Hunter Mack. "Artificial Neural Network Models for Octane Number and Octane Sensitivity: A Quantitative Structure Property Relationship Approach to Fuel Design". *Journal of Energy Resources Technology* (2023). https://doi.org/10.1115/1.4062189
- PB10. **Travis Kessler**, Amina SubLaban, J. Hunter Mack. "Predicting the Cetane Number, Sooting Tendency, and Energy Density of Terpene Fuel Additives". *ASME Internal Combustion Engine Division Fall Technical Conference* (2022). https://doi.org/10.1115/ICEF2022-91163
- PB9. **Travis Kessler**, Thomas Schwartz, Hsi-Wu Wong, J. Hunter Mack. "Evaluating Diesel/Biofuel Blends Using Artificial Neural Networks and Linear/Nonlinear Equations". *ASME Internal Combustion Engine Division Fall Technical Conference* (2021). https://doi.org/10.1115/ICEF2021-67785
- PB8. **Travis Kessler**, Thomas Schwartz, Hsi-Wu Wong, J. Hunter Mack. "Predicting the Cetane Number, Yield Sooting Index, Kinematic Viscosity, and Cloud Point for Catalytically Upgraded Pyrolysis Oil Using Artificial Neural Networks". *ASME Internal Combustion Engine Division Fall Technical Conference* (2020). https://doi.org/10.1115/ICEF2020-2978
- PB7. **Travis Kessler**, Peter C. St. John, Junqing Zhu, Charles S. McEnally, Lisa D. Pfefferle, J. Hunter Mack. "A comparison of computational models for predicting yield sooting index". *Proceedings of the Combustion Institute* (2020). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.proci.2020.07.009
- PB6. **Travis Kessler**, Thomas Schwartz, Hsi-Wu Wong, J. Hunter Mack. "Screening Compounds for Fast Pyrolysis and Catalytic Biofuel Upgrading Using Artificial Neural Networks". *ASME Internal Combustion Engine Division Fall Technical Conference* (2019). https://doi.org/10.1115/ICEF2019-7170
- PB5. Sanskriti Sharma, Hernan Gelaf-Romer, **Travis Kessler**, J. Hunter Mack. "ECabc: A feature tuning program focused on Artificial Neural Network hyperparameters". *Journal of Open Source Software* (2019). https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.01420
- PB4. **Travis Kessler**, Eric Sacia, Alexis Bell, J. Hunter Mack. "Artificial neural network based predictions of cetane number for furanic biofuel additives". Fuel, 206, 171-179 (2017). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fuel.2017.06.015
- PB3. **Travis Kessler**, Gregory Dorian, J. Hunter Mack. "Application of a Rectified Linear Unit (ReLU) Based Artificial Neural Network to Cetane Number Predictions". *ASME Internal Combustion Engine Division Fall Technical Conference* (2017). https://doi.org/10.1115/icef2017-3614
- PB2. **Travis Kessler**, J. Hunter Mack. "ECNet: Large scale machine learning projects for fuel property prediction". Journal of Open Source Software (2017). https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.00401
- PB1. **Travis Kessler**, Eric Sacia, Alexis Bell, J. Hunter Mack. "Predicting the Cetane Number of Furanic Biofuel Candidates Using an Improved Artificial Neural Network Based on Molecular Structure". ASME Internal Combustion Engine Division Fall Technical Conference (2016). https://doi.org/10.1115/icef2016-9383